Guide to the University of Chicago School of Social Service Administration WIN Program Records 1969-1973
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. School of Social Service Administration. WIN Program. Records
1969-1973
1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Work Incentive Program (WIN) was established by the U.S. Department of Labor in 1967-1968 to increase employability and employment among those receiving welfare. The University of Chicago's School of Social Service Administration (SSA) was involved with the administration of Illinois' WIN program. This collection contains clippings, conference proceedings, correspondence, data analysis, papers, and reports. It includes material generated at panel meetings with the University of Michigan's School of Social Work and Case Western University's School of Applied Social Science. Material spans 1969-1973.
Information on Use
Access
Box 4 contains salary information, restricted until 2020.
The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Historical Note
The Work Incentive Program (WIN) was established by the U.S. Department of Labor in 1967-1968. WIN was designed to increase employability and employment among those receiving welfare under Aid to Families with Dependent Children (AFDC). It required states to offer job training and job-seeking assistance. A voluntary program until 1971, incentives for participation ranged from exemptions in calculating AFDC need to actual incentive payments. WIN programs were federally funded and locally administered by employment services and social services.
As a research institution and public service provider, the University of Chicago's School of Social Service Administration (SSA) was involved with local administration of the WIN program. Working closely with the University of Michigan's School of Social Work and Case Western University's School of Applied Social Science, SSA produced a number of reports on the program's administration and its efficacy on the ground.
The WIN Program met with widespread criticism and was generally recognized as having failed to accomplish its intended goals. By the early 1970s it was clear that many enrollees were not finding jobs. Amendments to the Social Security Act in 1971, 1980, 1982, and 1984 attempted to improve program administration. By 1990 it had been phased out by a new program, Job Opportunities and Basic Skills (JOBS).
Scope Note
The collection consists of records of SSA's administrative role in the WIN Program from 1969-1973. These files were kept by William Reid, a former SSA faculty member. Much of the material relates to conferences and panel meetings held jointly with the University of Michigan's School of Social Work and Case Western University's School of Applied Social Science. Materials include correspondence, minutes, reports, clippings, and publications. Files are arranged alphabetically.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
University of Chicago. School of Social Service Administration. Records. 1969-1978
Subject Headings
Reid, William James, 1928-; University of Chicago. School of Social Service Administration; Welfare employment programs; Work Incentive Program (U.S.)
INVENTORY
- Client forms, blank, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Clippings, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Computer costs, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Conference on Manpower Programs, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Conference on Manpower Services for the Welfare Poor, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
- Correspondence, Council on Social Work Education, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, Minneapolis Institute for Interdisciplinary Studies, 1971-1972, Folders11-14: Data analysis, 1970-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Panel meetings, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
- Panel meeting, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Panel meetings, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
- Panel meetings, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Panel meeting, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "ADFC Mothers View the Work Incentive Program," 1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "The Client's Assessment of Incentives to Participate in WIN," 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "Comment on Study of Decision Making in the WIN Program," 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "Decision Making in the WIN Program," 1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Decision Making in the WIN Program," 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "Differential Career Patterns of Male, Female, and Youth WIN Enrollees," 1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "The Female WIN Enrollee: Career Patterns and Career Planning," undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "Maximizing Client and Program Congruency," 1971 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- "The Movement of ADFC Mothers To and Through the Cook County WIN Program," undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- "Powerlessness and Violent Attitudes in Urban America," 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "Professional Welfare Orientation and an Attitude of Work Alienation Among Public Welfare Workers," 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Progress Reports, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
- "A Review of the Decision Making Process in the WIN Program," 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- "Structural Factors in Non-Compliance in Referring Client to Programs," 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- "WIN Appeal to the Illinois Department of Public Aid," 1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Budgets and salaries, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)